Register of the Jack Kramer papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Jack Kramer papers
circa 1960-1969
1968-1969
68016
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box (0.4 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoranda, writings, printed matter, photographs, and one sound recording relating to the Eritrean Liberation Front and the movement for Eritrean independence. Also available on microfilm (1 reel).
Kramer, Jack.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Use copies of all sound recordings in this collection are available.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1968.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Forms of Material Available
Also available on microfilm (1 reel).
Biographical/Historical Note
Jack Kramer is an American journalist and author. He graduated from Stanford University with a B.A. in English in 1965 and completed graduate work in journalism at Columbia University in 1970. Kramer worked as a staff reporter for The Wall Street Journal, contributing editor for Time magazine, and Middle East Bureau chief for Bloomberg Businessweek. He covered a variety of subjects as a journalist in the 1960s, including Alabama during the Civil Rights Movement, Vietnam, Laos, Egypt, Eritrea, Somalia, Kenya, Rwanda, Tunisia, Algeria, Sudan, the Western Sahara, Greece, and Turkey. Kramer's publications include: Travels with the Celestial Dog, a memoir of the 1960s; Rwanda Means the Universe, with Louise Mushikiwabo, the current foreign minister of Rwanda; and business-related books.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Jack Kramer papers include correspondence, memoranda, writings, printed matter, photographs, and one unique sound recording recorded in Eritrea in September 1968. The recording has interviews with rank and file independence fighters and commanders such as Osman Mohammed Idris (aka Abu Shenab) of the Eritrean Liberation Front (E.L.F.), who were fighting for independence from Ethiopia. The correspondence include letters to and from Eritrean nationalists such as Woldeab Woldemariam, Kidane Kiflu, Mohamud Dinai, and Osman Saleh Sabbe.
Eritrean Liberation Front.; Tagādlo hārnat 'Értrā.; Eritrea--History.; Nationalism--Eritrea.; Phonotapes.
- Correspondence
  - Dinai, Mohamud, 1968 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Duignan, Peter, 1960s (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Kiflu, Kidane, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Sabbe, Osman Saleh, 1968 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Salih, Fathy Mohamed Ahmed, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Woldemariam, Woldeab, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 6)
- Memoranda
  - By the Eritrean Liberation Front for the Ethiopian Students Union in Europe, 1967 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - On Eritrea from the Eritrean Liberation Front office, Damascus, 1960s (Box-folder 1: 8)
- News Bulletins
  - Eritrea News Bulletin, nos. 73-76, 78-81, Eritrean Liberation Front, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - L'Erythrée Bulletin d'Information, nos. 76-83, Le Front de la Libération Érythréenne (F.L.E.), 1969 (Box-folder 1: 10)
- Reports
  - Eritrean refugees, statement by Mr. J. Jamison of the Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (U.N.H.C.R.), 1967 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Memorandum submitted by the delegations of Guatemala and Pakistan, United Nations Commission for Eritrea, republished by the Eritrean Liberation Front, 1960s (Box-folder 1: 12)
- Resolutions
  - The United Nations Federal Resolution for Eritrea, 390 A (V), 1950, republished by the Eritrean Liberation Front, 1960s (Box-folder 1: 13)
- Writings
  - A brief description of the progress of the "Battle of Halhal" camp, 1968 (Box-folder 1: 14)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes ambush map and pictures with the Eritrean Liberation Front fighters.
  - "A Letter to the United Nations Secretary General (U.N.S.G.)," Eritrean Liberation Front, 1960s (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - "Close to Million Victims: Sudan's Bloody Struggle Hushed," The Plain Dealer, 1969 February 21 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - "Constitution of Eritrea: Text of the Constitution of Eritrea as Adapted by the Eritrean Assembly on 10 July 1952," republished by the Eritrean Liberation Front, 1960s (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - "Crossroads of Africa: Ethiopia's Unknown War," The Nation, 1969 August 11 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - "Ethiopia's War of Extermination in Eritrea: Facts and Figures," Eritrean Liberation Front, 1960s (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - "Gallows in Eritrea: A Dramatic Grab of Bloody Reality, Narrated by a Swedish Journalist, Part One," Eritrean Liberation Front, 1960s (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - "Hidden War in Ethiopia," Venture, 1969 May (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Jack Kramer's report of his travel with members of the Eritrean Liberation Front, 1960s (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - "Peking Reds: Guerrilla College on a Spice Island," San Francisco Chronicle, 1968 December (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - "The Ethiopian Unilateral Abrogation of United Nations Federal Resolution," by Tedla Bairu, Eritrean Liberation Front, 1960s (Box-folder 1: 24)
  - "The Progressives Demand Radical Changes in the Eritrean Liberation Front,", 1968 (Box-folder 1: 25)
  - "Soviets Dispatch Navy Task Force to Suez Canal," San Francisco Sunday Examiner and Chronicle, 1968 December 15 (Box-folder 1: 26)
  - Transcription of interviews with Eritrean Liberation Front members and a map showing plan for the Front's attack, 1968 September (Box-folder 1: 27)
  - "Truths about the Decimation War in Eritrea," Eritrean Liberation Front, 1960s (Box-folder 1: 28)
  - "War South of Khartoum," San Francisco Examiner and Chronicle, 1969 February 16 (Box-folder 1: 29)
- Sound Recordings
  - Interview by Jack Kramer with Eritrean Liberation Front members, 1968 September (Box-folder 1: 30)
    Original magnetic tape cassette (sides 1 and 2) and open reel tapes #1 and #2 (copies). Includes voices, music, and interviews. Side 1: Kidane Kiflu, Jack Kramer, Abdella Hassan, Mohammed Ali Idris, atrocities testimonials from residents of Adi Ibrahim, Adi E'kut. Side 2: Introduction by Aberra Mekonnen, music by Mohammed Tahir, Tigre poetry reciting by Garfo, Saadia and Osman Mohammed Idris/Abu Sheneb.
    Access
    Use copy reference number: 68016_a_0011504